Guide to the Serge Chermayeff Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Serge Chermayeff papers
1957-1968
MS 1240
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.25
Chiefly printed copies of Serge Chermayeff's writings and research files on architecture. About half the papers consist of teaching materials from master class seminars in architecture conducted by Chermayeff at Yale University in 1966-1967.
Chermayeff, Serge, 1900-1996
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Art and Architecture Library, 1980.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Serge Chermayeff Papers consist largely of printed materials concerning his professional interests. In particular, there are copies of Chermayeff's writings, together with the research materials for one book, and teaching materials, especially records of master's class seminars at Yale in 1966-1967. Some of the printed material is annotated, but there are only a few original manuscripts or typescripts and little correspondence in the papers.
The papers were transferred from the Art and Architecture Library in October, 1980.
Biographical / Historical
Sergei Ivanovitch Issakovitch was born on October 8, 1900, in Grozny, then in Caucasia. He was educated in England, where he took the name of Serge Chermayeff at the suggestion of his guardian. By age thirty, Chermayeff had already become an established designer with his own architectural firm. He came to the United States in 1940, accepting a teaching position at Brooklyn College two years later. He stayed at Brooklyn College as professor and chairman of the department of design until 1946, when he moved to the Institute of Design in Chicago, where he was president for four years. In 1953, he became professor of architecture at Harvard University. He concluded his career as a professor at Yale University, where he taught between 1962 and 1969, at which time he became professor emeritus. He died on May 8, 1996.
Architecture -- Study and teaching; Architects; Educators; Chermayeff, Serge, 1900-1996; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. School of Fine Arts
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1968, n.y., undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Edward Frank letter enclosing his paper, "On Research and Development and the Construction Industry", 1967, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Writings
    - The Urban Family House: A Design Project (with Christopher Alexander): annotated, [ca. 1959] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "The New Nomads", 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Search for a New Urbanity: A Study by the Master's Class, Department of Architecture, Yale University (with Peter Leal Floyd): mock-up for printing with some Ms pages, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 5 - 6)
    - Shape of Community: Realization of Human Potential (with Alexander Tzonis)
      - Preface-chapter VI, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Chapter VII-appendices, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Teaching materials
    - Master's class, Department of Architecture, Yale University
      - Seminars: excerpts, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - General information, schedules, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Seminars: edited transcripts, hand-outs, reports
        - Seminar 1, 1966 October 3 (Box 2, Folder 11)
        - Seminar 2, 1966 October 17 (Box 2, Folder 12)
        - Seminar 3, 1966 October 31 (Box 2, Folder 13)
        - Seminar 4, 1966 November 14 (Box 2, Folder 14)
        - Seminar 5, 1966 November 28 (Box 2, Folder 15)
        - Seminar 6, 1966 December 12 (Box 2, Folder 16)
        - Seminar 7, 1967 January 9 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Final review, student comments, 1967 February 10 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Conferences, etc., in which Chermayeff participated: printed announcements, 1963, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Research materials
    - Shape of Community, 1960-1968, undated (Box 3, Folder 20 - 23)
    - Education for Urban Design: mimeographed conference proceedings, annotated, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Miscellaneous, 1965, 1966, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Writings about Serge Chermayeff, 1957, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 26)